Karl K. Knecht Papers
Karl K. Knecht Papers
1906-1966
Knecht, Karl K.
2 linear ft.
88 original editorial cartoons (1906-1960), correspondence (1926-1966) and two photographs (undated)
149108
Biographical History
Karl K. Knecht (1883-1972) was an American cartoonist.
Karl Kae Knecht was born in Iroquois, Dakota Territory on December 4, 1883 and grew up in Illinois. Knecht’s mother was an Irish immigrant and Knecht’s father owned a clothing store and drew cartoons to use in store advertisements. Knecht attended the Chicago Art Institute for three years and after publishing his first cartoon in 1905 in the Freeport (Illinois) Standard, Knecht went to work as the cartoonist at the Evansville Courier where his first cartoon appeared in September 1906.
In addition to drawing cartoons for the paper, Knecht became staff photographer in 1917 when the newspaper bought its first camera and also wrote columns and reviews. His "Say, Kay! What of Folks, Shows, Animals N' Such" column appeared weekly from 1919 until 1954. Knecht was named director of the paper and served as vice president from 1952 to 1960. For most of Knecht’s career, his cartoons appeared seven days a week on the front page until 1954 when they were moved to the editorial page. Knecht worked for the Courier for so long that he came to be known as the “dean of editorial cartoonists”.
Knecht was also involved with the circus. He helped organize the Circus Fans Association in 1925 and was both secretary-treasurer and president of that organization and produced its magazine, White Tops. He also helped found the Mesker Zoo in Evansville after he was given a pair of lions in the late 1920s.
Knecht was a member of Sigma Delta Chi and also a founding member of the Association of American Editorial Cartoonists. In 1953, Knecht received an honorary doctorate of humane letters from Evansville College and July 22, 1954 was proclaimed Karl Kae Knecht Day in Evansville, Indiana. He was also a supporter of numerous charitable causes and would at times use his cartoons to bring attention to these causes.
Karl Kae Knecht retired from the Courier in May 1960 and died in Evansville, Indiana on July 28, 1972.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Karl K. Knecht Papers consists of two series: Cartoons and Correspondence and Photographs.
Cartoons contains 88 original editorial cartoons dating from 1906 to 1960 with several undated cartoons at the end of the series. Generally, Knecht's cartoons were drawn on chalk plate from 1906 to 1912 and then with pen and ink. Dmensions vary. Knecht often included an elephant with his signature. Some sources have noted that this was due to Knecht's allegiance to the Republican Party while other sources have said the elephant was included as an homage to Knecht's interest in the circus and possible a reference to the elephants that were given to him. The circus was a motif Knecht frequently used to portray politics and a recurring character in Knecht's cartoons was Mr. Public who represented the way political decisions affected the common person.
Correspondence and Photographs is comprised of incoming letters arranged chronologically and two photographs. Notable correspondents include fellow cartoonists: Milton Caniff, Jay Norwood “Ding” Darling (1961) and John T. McCutcheon. Also included are letters from Clyde Beatty (1965), Eddie Cantor, Senator Albert B. Chandler, Joe Cook (vaudeville actor), Katherine Cornell, Representative Winfield K. Denton (1964), John Nance Garner (1940), J. Edgar Hoover, Representative Charles M. LaFollette, Representative Maury Maverick, John Ringling North, Henry Ringling North, and Tiffany Thayer. Knecht's work with circuses is a frequent topic and several letters were written on colored circus themed stationary.
Arrangement of the Collection
Both series are arranged chronologically with undated material appearing at the end.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Knecht, Karl K.; Einstein, Albert -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; United States. Congress -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Democratic National Committee (U.S.) -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Evansville Courier (Evansville, Ind.); American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Caricatures and cartoons -- Indiana.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Cartoonists -- Indiana.; Circus.; Editorial cartoons -- Indiana -- Evansville.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Holidays -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Political cartoons.; World politics -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Russia -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Correspondence.; Editorial cartoons.; Photographs.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mr. Karl K. Knecht, 1966.
Inventory
- Cartoons, Titles appearing in brackets are not official captions but rather prominent phrases or people mentioned in the cartoon.
  - 1906-1907 (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
    1906- Sep 29: Labor Day at Oyster Bay
    1907: The victor or our next president
  - 1912-1936 (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
    1912: Always Lurking About
    1912- Feb 29: [Leap Year]
    1920: [Christmas]
    1925: The Bryan/Darrow Trial, Dayton, Tennessee
    1927: [Lindy (Charles Lindbergh)]
    1932- May 16: [Aw! Gee! Wizz, Paw]
    1933: [Relief Fund]
    1933: Nov 28: Birds
    1934: [U.S. Migratory Bird Laws]
    1935- Oct 30: [Halloween]
    1936- Oct: [FDR]
  - 1938-1939 (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
    1938- Nov 17: [Today's Newspapers of the World]
    1939: A Circus Innovation: Air Conditioning
    1939- Feb 16: [The Fleet in Maneuvers Around the Panama Canal]
    1939- Mar 10: [The Flu]
    1939- Mar 17: [Hitler's New Home ]
    1939- May 19: Ben Hur
    1939- May 24: [Stand Pat on New Deal]
    1939: [Indiana politics]
  - 1940-1947 (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
    1940- Jun 5: [Hitler]
    1940- Jun 6: [Monroe Doctrine]
    1941- Apr 1: Animals and Circus Plus Theater
    1941- May 8: [Haile Selassie ]
    1941- Jul 14: [Joint Action Against Germany]
    1943- Oct 28: [Yugoslavia]
    1946- Oct 28: Caught in a Whirlwind
    1946- Nov 14: [Politics]
    1947- Apr 18: When Will We Learn
    1947- Jul 3: [Old Time Fourth of July]
  - 1949-1951 (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
    1949- Jan 25: [Republican National Committee]
    1949- Apr 29: [Leaving China]
    1949- May 13: Blue Cross Blue Shield
    1949- May 19: [Tammany of NYC -- FDR, Jr.]
    1950: Across the Horizon
    1950: [Noah's Ark]
    1950- Mar 17: [Come Back to Erin]
    1950- Mar 22: [Evansville, Indiana]
    1950- Sep 16: Closed and Open Books
    1951- Sep 3: Labor Day
  - 1952-1953 (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
    1952- Jun 28: [Police Fund Charity]
    1952- Jul 4: [Abraham Lincoln]
    1953- May 26: [French Cabinet Crisis]
    1953: [The Great Outdoors]
    1953- Jun 5: [United Nations]
    1953- Jun 7: [Education]
    1953- Jun 13: [Ike on a Fishing Trip]
    1953- Aug: "No!"
    1953- Sep 10: [Jewish New Year]
  - 1954-1955 (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
    1954- Feb 9: "A-Men-!"
    1954- May 18: [A Rival]
    1954- Nov: [Thanksgiving]
    1955: [Arbitration]
    1955- Apr 19: [Einstein]
    1955- Jun: [Tell th' boys I'll be home soon- with lots to tell, an' to look at the situation over]
    Aug 5: Which will Kentucky choose?
    1955- Nov 4: Time to Change Again
    1955- Dec 6: Bound to Be a Few Discordant Notes at First
  - 1956-1957 (Oversize 1, Folder 8)
    1956- Jan 2: There are Other Mirrors, Look!
    1956- Aug 31: How Time Doth Fly
    1956- Oct 17: Not the Time for That!
    1956- Oct 24: When the Big "Poles" Snap, Look Out
    1957- May 17: Their Days
    1957- Nov 1: Get It Out from Under the Stack
    1957- Nov 13: Not Quite "Second Table," But...!
    1957- Nov 16: At Least Get His Belt Buckled
  - 1958-1959 (Oversize 1, Folder 9)
    1958- Apr 12: Mr. X Senator, How did your folk react, to unemployment and taxes? Mr. X Congressman, How did your's react to recession and high prices?
    1958- Apr 16: A Blotch! Botch!
    1958- May 31: The French Merry-Go-Round
    1958- Nov 26: Turkey Time Traffic Tie-up
    1958- Dec 24: There Is a Santa Claus
    1959- Jan 7: What I Say Is, Please Forget About 1960!
    1959- Jan 20: To Tip the Balance
    1959- Mar 25: Holy Week
    1959- Sep 3: Now For the Top Mounter of "the Big Four"
  - 1960; undated (Oversize 1, Folder 10)
    1960: As of Today
    1960- May 6: Bump--bump--bumping Along
    1960- May 10: Is My Face Red!
    1960- May 14: At Least Start to Bury It!
    1960- May 19: Reverting to Type!
    1960- May 26: Can't Run From the Shadow -- As Long As Such a Sun Shines
    year unknown- May 26: [Herr Hitler]
    [Hallowe'en]
    If this...why not this...?
    [I've Decided to Handle Your Letters From the Little Ones]
    [Storm Clouds]
    [Juvenile Delinquency]
- Correspondence and photographs, Written comments and annotations appear on many pieces of correspondence with further details about the correspondent.
  - Correspondence, 1926; 1929-1933,; 1935-1939 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1943; 1947 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Undated (Box 1)
  - Photograph of Knecht, Undated (Box 1)
  - Photograph of cartoon "His Only Hope"- marked as first cartoon- Evansville Courier, Undated (Box 1)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may require you to browse with alternative terms.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
Adenauer, Konrad B1F9
AFL-CIO B1F7
airline industry B1F9
armed forces B1F8
birds B1F2
Blue Cross Blue Shield B1F5
Bricker, John W. B1F7
Britain B1F4-B1F5 B1F8
Bryan, William Jennings B1F1
cancer B1F4
Chandler, Sr., Albert Benjamin "Happy" B1F7
charity B1F2 B1F6 B1F9
children B1F2 B1F8
China B1F2 B1F5-B1F6
Christmas B1F2 B1F9-B1F10
Churchill, Winston B1F6
circus B1F3 B1F7
communism B1F6
Congress B1F4 B1F7-B1F9
Coolidge, Calvin B1F6
Daley, Richard J. B1F10
de Gaulle, Charles B1F9
delinquency B1F9-B1F10
democracy B1F1
Democratic Party B1F2-B1F3 B1F9-B1F10
diseases B1F3
economy B1F9
education B1F6
Einstein, Albert B1F7
Eisenhower, Dwight B1F6 B1F8-B1F10
elections B1F10
Ethiopia B1F4
Formosa B1F5
Fourth of July B1F4 B1F6
France B1F6 B1F9
Germany B1F4 B1F6
government spending B1F8-B1F9
Halloween B1F10
Hitler, Adolph B1F3-B1F4 B1F10
Holy Week B1F9
Humphrey, Hubert B1F10
hunting B1F2
Indiana B1F3 B1F5 B1F7 B1F10
Indiana State Convention B1F3
Ireland B1F5
Japan B1F4
Jews B1F3 B1F6
Kennedy, John F. B1F10
Kentucky B1F7
Khrushchev, Nikita B1F10
Korean War B1F5-B1F6
Labor Day B1F5
Landon, Alf B1F2
leap year B1F2
Lewis, John B1F7
Lincoln, Abraham B1F6
Lindbergh, Charles B1F2
MacArthur, Douglas B1F5
MacMillan, Harold B1F9
March of Dimes B1F8
McCarthy, Joseph B1F7
Meany, George B1F7
Mihalovic B1F4
Monroe Doctrine B1F4
Morse, Wayne B1F10
National Rifle Association B1F2
NATO B1F8
Nazism B1F3-B1F4
New Deal B1F3
New York City B1F5
Nixon, Richard M. B1F10
nuclear weapons B1F8
Panama Canal B1F3
park board B1F10
police B1F6
polio B1F8
politicians B1F8
politics B1F4 B1F8
prices B1F9
progress B1F7
railroad industry B1F7
Republican Party B1F3 B1F5
Reuther, Walter B1F7
Roosevelt Jr., Franklin D. B1F5
Roosevelt, Franklin D. B1F2-B1F3
Roosevelt, Theodore B1F1
Rosh Hashanah B1F6
Russia B1F4-B1F6 B1F8 B1F10
science B1F8
Scopes trial B1F2
Selassie, Haile B1F4
South Dakota B1F6
Soviet Union B1F8
Stevenson, Adlai E. B1F8 B1F10
strikes B1F7 B1F9
summer B1F6-B1F7
Symington, Stuart B1F10
taxes B1F9
Thanksgiving B1F7
Titanic B1F2
Tito, Josip Broz B1F4
transportation B1F5
Truman, Harry S. B1F4 B1F7
Twining, Nathan Farragut B1F7
U.S. Mail B1F10
unemployment B1F9
unions B1F5
United Nations B1F5-B1F6
weather B1F10
women B1F8
Yugoslavia B1F4